{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Pierre Landais [[lahn-DEH]] supported a rebellion against this man by the Duke of Brittany. This husband of Anne Neville faced a revolt by the Duke of Buckingham after this man seized the throne from the child of his brother, Edward IV. In late 2012, this man's skeleton was identified beneath the former site of Greyfriars Church. A landing at Milford Haven in 1485 was a precursor to this man becoming the last English king to die in battle. For ten points, name this man who lost the Battle of Bosworth Field to the future Tudor king, Henry VII.",
      "answer": "Richard III"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure revealed the island of Anaphe [[AH-nah-feh]] in order to shelter the Argonauts. Heracles completed his labors for Eurystheus [[yoo-RISS-thee-us]] at this being's command. This deity won a music contest against Pan and turned King Midas's ears into those of a donkey. The patron deity of Delphi, this figure was often conflated with Helios, god of the sun. For ten points, name this Greek god of prophecy, archery, and music, the twin brother of Artemis.",
      "answer": "Apollo or Apollon"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of this decade, Amalia Post led a successful campaign to enact women's suffrage in the Wyoming Territory, though the lack of nationwide women’s enfranchisement led Elizabeth Cady Stanton to oppose the 15th amendment which was passed during this decade. Activism in this decade followed a four-year conflict that ended with the assassination of Abraham Lincoln following the surrender of Robert E. Lee. For ten points, name this decade during which Reconstruction began after the U.S. Civil War.",
      "answer": "1860s"
    },
    {
      "question": "Graham Stevenson criticized this show for erroneously portraying Winston Churchill as Home Secretary during one period. In this series, December 3, 1919, is decided upon as Black Star Day on which one group challenges Billy Kimber’s pitches at the Worcester [[WOO-ster]] Races. Sam Neill portrays an Ulster Protestant policeman in this show following and titled for an historical street gang comprised of working class men who dressed in distinctive tailored clothes. For ten points, name this BBC crime drama which focuses on historical rivalries in Birmingham.",
      "answer": "Peaky Blinders 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, Shig Murao [[myuh-RAO]] was arrested for selling an \"obscene\" book written by a local author, but Judge Clayton Horn ruled that Howl was protected by the First Amendment. This city's Beyond Shelter anti-drugs program was created by its mayor, Art Agnos, and Lawrence Ferlinghetti co-founded this city's City Lights bookstore. A large Finnish community used to live in this city's Castro district, and this city was the location of the Summer of Love in its Haight [[HATE]]-Ashbury district. For ten points, name this city in northern California.",
      "answer": "San Francisco"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man established rakuichi [[rah-koo-EE-chee]] open markets and rakuza guilds. Straw dummy troops and a thunderstorm helped this man win the Battle of Okehazama [[oh-keh-hah-ZAH-mah]], where he first noticed the talents of his sandal-bearer, who later succeeded him. Akechi Mitsuhide [[ah-KEH-chee mih-tsoo-HEE-deh]] caught this man in Kyoto and forced his suicide in the Honnō-ji Incident. For ten points, name this Japanese daimyo [[DIE-myoh]] and unifier who preceded the rule of Toyotomi Hideyoshi [[toh-yoh- TOH-mee hih-deh-YOH-shee]].",
      "answer": [
        "Oda Nobunaga",
        "either underlined portion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Jean McCormick claimed that a group of unsent letters this person wrote proved that she was this person's child. A rescue of Captain Egan may have led to the best known nickname given to this figure, who was said to have chased Jack McCall with a meat cleaver after McCall murdered an acquaintance. This woman was once employed as an assistant to a madam in Deadwood, where she had arrived as part of a wagon train including \"Wild Bill\" Hickok. For ten points, name this storyteller from Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show.",
      "answer": [
        "Calamity Jane",
        "Martha Jane Cannary"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A party that has called for a parliamentary system in this country is the Democratic Patriots' Movement. The death of Chokri Belaid [[beh-lah-EED]] in this country led to accusations that the perpetrators were linked to the Ennahda Movement. In 2015, twenty tourists were killed in a terrorist attack on this country’s Bardo National Museum. Zine [[ZEE-neh]] El Abidine [[ah-bih-DEE-neh]] Ben Ali was ousted as leader of this country following protests that began after a street vendor set himself on fire in 2011. The Arab Spring began in, for ten points, what North African country?",
      "answer": "Republic of Tunisia 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "It's not fish, but the Matafère [[mah-tah-FEHR]] Tower was constructed to protect workers who collected this good. False bottoms known as faux culls were often worn by women who smuggled this good, a crime punishable by up to ten years on a galley. This good was collected in provincial granaries before it was sold with a tax known as the gabelle. Faux saunage [[foh soh-NAWZH]] involved the fraudulent upselling of, for ten points, what food preservative often found in mines and seawater?",
      "answer": [
        "Salt",
        "Sodium Chloride"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "George Crawford was appointed Secretary of War by this president, but later resigned due to the Galphin Affair. The State of Deseret was founded during the presidency of this man who had defeated Democrat Lewis Cass. Many historians believe that bad water from the Washington sewers caused this man’s death by cholera. For his victories during the Second Seminole War, this man earned the nickname “Old Rough and Ready.” For ten points, name this twelfth U.S. president, who was elected in 1848.",
      "answer": "Zachary Taylor 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A variant of this holiday is celebrated in Latin America as Día de la Raza. The first parade for this holiday was established by Nicola Larco in San Francisco, and in 2017, the city of Akron drew the ire of its Italian-American community by attempting to replace this holiday with Indigenous Peoples’ Day. Usually held in October, this day is widely celebrated on the island of Hispaniola. For ten points, name this holiday which commemorates a man who was long thought to have discovered the New World in 1492.",
        "answer": [
          "Columbus Day",
          "Day of the Race",
          "Dia de la Raza"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "La Navidad, the settlement established by Columbus's men on Hispaniola, was built from the remains of the Santa Maria. It was located in this modern-day country, the only nation in history to be established by a successful slave revolt.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Haiti",
          "République d'Haïti",
          "Repiblik d Ayiti"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These events were intentionally ignored by General Anton Denikin during the White Terror, as he believed the victims to be communists. An early example of these events occurred when residents of Strasbourg believed that certain residents engaged in \"host desecration\" and \"blood libel.\" In the nineteenth century, the Pale of Settlement became a hotbed for these violent reprisals, which were motivated by antisemitism. For ten points, name these massacres of Jewish populations in Eastern Europe.",
        "answer": "Pogroms"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This major Black Sea port city in Ukraine experienced a century of pogroms due to a revival of Medieval antisemitism. This city was the site of the uprising of the crew of the battleship Potemkin.",
        "answer": "Odessa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's collaboration with Hilda Solis led to a $10 million fund to provide illegal immigrants with legal assistance. In Echo Park, this man helped create Historic Filipinotown. Antonio Villaraigosa [[vee-yah-rai-GOH-sah]] preceded this man as mayor of a certain city, the first Jewish holder of that position. In 2020, this man claimed “this is not 1992” as part of a promise to not deploy the National Guard as had been done during his city’s Rodney King Riots. For ten points, name this Los Angeles mayor, elected in 2013.",
        "answer": "Eric Michael Garcetti"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was elected mayor of Los Angeles in 1973 and held that office until 1993, the only Black person to be elected to that office as of 2021, as well as the longest-tenured mayor in LA history.",
        "answer": "Thomas \"Tom\" Bradley 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The last ruler with this title, Mahmud IV, met his downfall at the hands of the kingdom of Djenné [[jeh-NEH]], which was supported by Moroccan fusiliers. The first man to hold this royal title led a confederation of Mandinka people in their attempt to subjugate the Sosso king Sumanguru, leading to a victory at Kirina. A man with this title devalued the worth of gold in Egypt due to his generosity while on hajj. For ten points, gave this term for a Malian ruler, held by men such as Musa I.",
        "answer": [
          "Mansa",
          "Mansa Musa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This mansa, who founded the Keita Dynasty, names a Mandinka epic passed down via oral tradition by Malian griots.",
        "answer": [
          "Sundiata ] Keita",
          "Keita",
          "Konaté in place of Keita"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these texts describes an apocalyptic “War of Divisions.\" The Community Rule is one of these texts, the finding of which led to a reassessment of accusations that a work presented by Moses Shapira was a forgery. A group of Bedouins discovered these works in a series of twelve caves in Qumran [[KOOM-ron]]. Debates exist as to whether the Zadokites or the Essenes are responsible for these texts, most of which are housed in the Shrine of the Book in Jerusalem. For ten points, name these Jewish manuscripts found in the West Bank along a namesake body of water.",
        "answer": [
          "Dead Sea Scrolls",
          "Qumran Cave Scrolls before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the first of the Dead Sea Scrolls to be identified contains the oldest complete copy of this Biblical book. Today this book is considered the first of the Major Prophets in the Old Testament and is the source of much of the text of Handel's Messiah.",
        "answer": "Book of Isaiah or Sefer Yeshayahu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An employee of this company named John Rabe helped rescue victims during the Nanking Massacre. This company's founder created a dynamo that did not require permanent magnets, independently of Charles Wheatstone, and invented a form of telegraphy that relied on needles rather than Morse Code. An alternator built by this company powered the first instance of street lighting, which occurred in the United Kingdom. One of this company's factories in Bobreck was among those worked by prisoners at Auschwitz. Based in Bavaria, for ten points, what is this German industrial conglomerate?",
        "answer": "Siemens AG"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Werner von Siemens, the founder of Siemens AG, is the namesake of the SI unit of this measure of the ease with which electrical current passes.",
        "answer": [
          "Electrical Conductance",
          "Conductivity 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city contains tree-like structures that house plant beds in Supertree Grove, part of the Gardens by the Bay enhancement program announced by Prime Minister Lee Hsien [[she-EN]] Loong in 2005. This city gave its name to the British naval defense plan for their eastern empire after World War One. Stamford Raffles established a trading post at what became this city on the eastern end of the Strait of Malacca. Off the southern tip of the Malay Peninsula, for ten points, what is this city-state in southeast Asia which has been self- governed since 1959?",
        "answer": "Republic of Singapore or Republik Singapura"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Due to their rapid growth from the 1960s to the 1990s, Singapore, Taiwan, South Korea, and Hong Kong became known as the \"Four Asian [these animals],\" serving as role models to developing countries who became known as \"[This animal] Cub Economies.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Tigers also",
          "Four Little Dragons"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In what is now this state, Peter Parker and Henry Clinton’s forces were rebuffed from taking a city due to William Moultrie’s defense of a namesake fort on Sullivan’s Island. Over five thousand Continental troops under Benjamin Lincoln were captured at a siege in this state, in which the guerilla tactics of native son Francis Marion earned him the nickname \"the Swamp Fox.” The Battles of Waxhaws and Camden were fought in, for ten points, what state which also faced the Siege of Charleston?",
        "answer": "South Carolina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Banastre [[BAH-nah-ster]] Tarleton's brigade was devastated by a \"double envelopment\" at this late-Revolutionary War battle in modern-day Upstate South Carolina. This battle, and the ensuing Battle of King's Mountain, forced the British army north toward their ultimate defeat.",
        "answer": "Battle of Cowpens"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Regarding U.S. vice presidents, name the person who...",
      "prompt": "Concerning Regarding U.S. vice presidents, name the person who......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is America's second Catholic president who earlier served under Barack Obama.",
          "answer": "Joseph \"Joe\" Biden, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as Attorney General of California from 2011 to 2017.",
          "answer": "Kamala Harris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Accidentally shot Harry Whittington while hunting.",
          "answer": "Richard \"Dick\" Cheney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Made the American public aware of the threat of global warming in An Inconvenient Truth.",
          "answer": "Albert \"Al\" Gore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was told \"Senator, you're no Jack Kennedy\" by Lloyd Bentsen in a 1988 debate.",
          "answer": "James Danforth \"Dan\" Quayle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resigned from office while serving under Nixon.",
          "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resigned three months before Andrew Jackson's first term ended.",
          "answer": "John Caldwell Calhoun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the only VP other than Schuyler [[SKY-ler]] Colfax who also served as Speaker of the House.",
          "answer": "John Nance Garner 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Daily Life in Ancient Greece",
      "prompt": "Concerning the daily life of people in Ancient Greece, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Fruit whose oil was used to fuel lamps.",
          "answer": "Olives"
        },
        {
          "question": "Facility for training and socializing for male athletes.",
          "answer": [
            "Gymnasium",
            "Gymnasia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sport practiced at a palaestra, for which it was also named.",
          "answer": "Wrestling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central public space whose name means \"assembly.\"",
          "answer": "Agora"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stadium for horse and chariot racing.",
          "answer": "Hippodrome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Structure whose name means \"singing place,\" commonly used today for movie theatres.",
          "answer": "Odeon"
        },
        {
          "question": "God of medicine commonly prayed to for healing.",
          "answer": [
            "Asclepius",
            "Hepius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Form of tunic fastened at the shoulder.",
          "answer": [
            "Chitoniskos",
            "Peplos",
            "Doric",
            "Ionic chiton 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Apostles",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Apostles of Jesus Christ, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man whose name was originally Simon.",
          "answer": [
            "Simon Peter",
            "Cephas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Apostle from Tarsus, named Saul prior to his conversion.",
          "answer": "Paul"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Doubting\" man believed to have ministered in India.",
          "answer": [
            "Doubting Thomas",
            "Didymus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Traditional author of both the Book of Revelation and the only non-Synoptic Gospel.",
          "answer": [
            "John of Patmos",
            "John the Revelator",
            "John the Divine",
            "John the Theologian"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name shared by two apostles, one a son of Alphaeus, the other of Zebedee.",
          "answer": [
            "James",
            "Ya'akov",
            "Iakobos"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Patron saint of Scotland whose symbol is an X-shaped cross.",
          "answer": [
            "Andrew, the First-Called",
            "Andreas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Apostle flayed alive for converting an Armenian king.",
          "answer": "Bartholomew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man chosen to replace Judas Iscariot.",
          "answer": [
            "Matthias",
            "Mattityahu"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote the memoir Advance and Retreat partly in response to claims made by Joseph Johnston. Wounds that this man sustained at Chickamauga led to the (20 pts)",
        "amputation of his right leg. A failed “Pickett’s Charge of the West” was conducted by this man’s troops at his disastrous defeat at Franklin. That defeat occurred a month before this man was defeated in a December 1864 battle against his former instructor (10 pts)",
        "George Thomas at Nashville. For ten points, name this Confederate general known for his reckless aggressiveness."
      ],
      "answer": "John Bell Hood"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Muslim mythology, this man was a Palestinian disciple of Christ who was killed three times by the king of Mosul, only to resurrect himself each time. According to tradition, this saint served as a member of (20 pts)",
        "Diocletian’s Praetorian Guard until he was sentenced to death after not renouncing his Christian faith. Crusader states like the Genoese Republic used this saint’s (10 pts)",
        "namesake cross as their ensign. For ten points, name this Catholic saint who legendarily slayed a dragon in Libya."
      ],
      "answer": "Saint George of Lydda"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s first spaceflight was as a pilot on Gemini 10. This man was the first person to conduct multiple space walks and designed a mission patch based on an illustration from Water, Prey, and Game Birds of North America. A book of 18 (20 pts)",
        "rendezvous scenarios was created by this man, who was the subject of the quote \"not since Adam has any human known such (10 pts)",
        "solitude.\" Alone in the Columbia while the Eagle descended, for ten points, what man was the crewmate of Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong during Apollo 11?"
      ],
      "answer": "Michael Collins"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this government, a merger between the Parti Communiste and the Radical Socialists was overseen by Jewish prime minister Leon Blum. With Great Britain, this government agreed to pursue the policy of appeasement and award Germany the (20 pts)",
        "Sudetenland under Édouard Daladier [[dah-lah-DYEH]]. This government was first established during the chaos of the (10 pts)",
        "Franco-Prussian War and the fall of Emperor Napoleon III’s regime. For ten points, name this government which collapsed after Nazi Germany’s 1940 invasion of France and was succeeded by the Vichy government."
      ],
      "answer": "French Third Republic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Six Steeds of Zhao Mausoleum was made in this dynasty, and a form of lead-glazed \"egg-and-spinach\" pottery known as sancai is particularly associated with this dynasty. One of this dynasty's kilns was located at Tongguan, and this dynasty's Giant Wild Goose Pagoda survived the (20 pts)",
        "1556 Shaanxi [[SHAHN-SHE]] Earthquake. A poet from this dynasty wrote \"Waking from Drunkenness on a Spring Day\" and a work which begins \"Before my bed there's a pool of light,\" the poem (10 pts)",
        "\"Quiet Night Thought.\" For ten points, Li Bai wrote during what Chinese dynasty?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tang ] Dynasty",
        "Tang Empire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One portion of this trail that passed along the Purgatoire [[PER-guh-twah]] River was referred to as the Mountain Route. A pioneer of this trail named William Becknell left from the Boonslick region near one of its termini at Franklin. (20 pts)",
        "Comanche traders collected tolls along this route, which contained Fort Dodge. This trail was rendered largely obsolete in 1880 with the advent of the (10 pts)",
        "railroad in its central region. Passing through Colorado and Kansas en route to the Missouri River, for ten points, what trail had an end in a namesake New Mexico city?"
      ],
      "answer": "Santa Fe Trail"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Hotel of York was the site of negotiations for this treaty, of which the resolution of debts and the opening of the Mississippi River were key negotiating points. Concessions in present-day (20 pts)",
        "states including Ohio helped double the size of one party’s territory in this treaty with the cession of the Northwest Territory. The Comte de Rochambeau [[roh-shahm-BOH]] helped bring about this treaty by assisting one side in defeating the forces of (10 pts)",
        "Charles Cornwallis at Yorktown. For ten points, name this treaty which ended the American Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "Treaty of Paris of 1783"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's government required the blind and deaf to be educated in the Elementary Education Act. After Secretary Cavendish was assassinated, this man ordered arbitrary detainment via the Irish Coercion Act. This man attacked the (20 pts)",
        "Bulgarian Horrors of the Ottomans in the Midlothian Campaign, bombarded Alexandria, and, in his second ministry, fought the Mahdi in Sudan. Extending voting to (10 pts)",
        "laborers in the 1884 Reform Act, for ten points, who was this \"Murderer of Gordon,\" a Liberal British prime minister and rival of Benjamin Disraeli?"
      ],
      "answer": "William Ewart Gladstone 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 3"
    }
  ]
}